what ethical considerations should be
taken into account when prescribing
hormone therapy particularly regarding
long-term effects and
dependency anytime you do anything for
another human being ethics come into
play and you should always practice
ethically you should always have the
patient's best interest at heart there
should be no outside factors that drive
your decision-making process when I say
decisionmaking process it is the
decision to either prescribe or not
prescribe the decision to actually move
forward with a treatment not always lies
with the patient themselves patients
have the right to deny any treatment and
you do not decide if someone will do
something or not you decide if you're
willing to help them in the process your
decision should always be driven by
ethics and those ethics should be based
with an end goal of doing the right
thing for the patient to improve their
quality of life and improve their
health sometimes it's contradictory
palea of care is a common example where
you may improve quality of life
but you're going to harm their health
but this is an end of life type of a
treatment what we're doing here is kind
of like it's not it's it's not paleo of
care and it's not exactly look you're
sick and I'm just going to treat you for
better health because if you look at
some treatments like cancer you're being
treated with chemotherapy they are
worsening your quality of life
transiently but they're improving your
health long term we're right in the
middle we're kind of we're kind of
saying look we believe that we're
improving your quality of life
but at the same time we're also
lengthening your life that's what we
truly believe and we do have literature
to support it as with anything in
medicine when you have literature
supporting one side you're going to have
another one you know against so it's
really hard to look at evidence-based
medicine the way they want us to look at
it and say what does the evidence show
well the evidence is always usually
going to show both uh it kind of depends
on how you interpret it so you know we
we hate to debate the philosophy of it
we just look at honestly after thousands
of case studies we looked at the
anecdotal evidence how do people feel
what is their their time span what is
their longevity what are other health
markers doing so we notice that when we
induce properly administered key term I
cannot emphasize enough properly
administered testosterone therapy
properly administered properly
management with good oversight because
the term trt gets tossed around it means
nothing unless we know the specifics so
properly administered properly managed
properly supervised trt we've noticed a
handful of things number one symptom
resolution is generally achieved in a
relatively short period of time number
two we notice that a lot of markers in
other Arenas improve anemas are reversed
sexual dysfunctions are reversed quality
of life is enhanced mood and cognition
are enhanced people are starting to now
throw away prescription
medications hypertension is improved and
people are starting to now come off some
of their anti-hypertensives people have
come off of stance people have come off
antis psychotics ssris
snris um Benzel they've tossed these
drugs which generally just masked an
underlying problem once their
hormonal balance has been restored so
ethically I am completely confident in
our decision to help somebody with
treatment if they are one symptomatic
and two especially if they show clear
signs
of suboptimal levels you don't always
have to have a clinical deficiency to be
treated suboptimal is very subjective
and if you are symptomatic and I see no
harm in treating you because he used the
word dependence nobody is dependent on
anything when it comes to this you're
not a type 1 diabetic who will die
without insulin you're using
testosterone if you stop taking
testosterone you're not going to die so
you're not dependent the quality of your
life may feel like it's dependent but
you're not dependent you are dependent
on food water air shelter you will die
without those things you're certainly
not dependent on your testosterone you
can come off and you can probably even
start producing your own levels again
the problem is if you were suboptimal to
start you're going to be suboptimal if
you stop so you're you're certainly not
dependent I know that scares a lot of
guys but if you got on for the right
reasons really you shouldn't be stopping
anyway just again make sure that it is
being treated by someone who understands
how to treat manage and supervise your
treatment on an ongoing basis your body
is always evolving your metrics are
always changing the variables are
changing metabolism changes shbg changes
your needs and your lifestyle changes
and understanding how to change things
on the fly to adapt to your
needs prevents bad side effects from
happening in the future and then
spending months trying to undo them with
someone else
[Music]